<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Python, startups, technology, Algeria and more | Redouane Zait</title><link href="http://redouanezait.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://redouanezait.com/feeds/all-en.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://redouanezait.com/</id><updated>2012-09-12T20:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Fennecs WebOs - A bad idea</title><link href="http://redouanezait.com/fennecs-webos-a-bad-idea.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-09-12T20:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Redouane Zait</name></author><id>tag:redouanezait.com,2012-09-12:fennecs-webos-a-bad-idea.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Fennecs is, or shall i say was &lt;em&gt;given its current status&lt;/em&gt; an algerian web based open source operating system project.
The project failed before even reaching a concretized project state, not a single line of code was written, there was just talk, The whole thing was merely an idea, a bad one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="operating-systems-101"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Operating systems 101&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know, the thing that bridges hardware with user written software, the one that handles memory management, schedules the CPU, presents the user with a &lt;em&gt;very nice&lt;/em&gt; filesystem tree abstraction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can such a thing run on top of a Web Browser with a sandboxed javascript interpreter ? it cannot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the project’s initial specs, it&amp;amp;rsquo;s merely a one page dashboard app, with a bunch of fancy widgets that interacts with third party API’s over HTTP, links to external web apps abstracted as applications with maybe icons and all that.
In the end, it all boils down to some html tags rendered by a browser engine that runs on top of a &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; operating system.
Calling and marketing it as an operating system is just silly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="open-source-101"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Open Source 101&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The road ahead for the project looked bumpy, dirty, and filled with all kind of obstacles. We’re talking mario kart kind of obstacles here, like bananas thrown and holes dug by other players in the game along the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and foremost there was a communication problem, using a facebook group as a communication mean for an open source software project is just as good as using C to write web apps.
sure, technically it’s doable, but not practical at all, it's just the wrong tool for the job.
IRC would’ve been much better, faster, and well suited for heated technical arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then problems associated with the decision making process saw the light, Decisions were made in a democratic fashion with voting polls open to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the right approach to elect presidents, but when it comes to &lt;em&gt;which technology shall we use&lt;/em&gt; kind of polls, I believe it’s not, and i’ll get to that later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coordination is very important in such projects, sadly there was none of it, everyone seemed to be on their own, with no clear and shared vision nor precise goals, people just did not know where to start.
That could have been prevented by forming a core developers team, that coordinates the project, assigns tasks, writes specifications, makes decisions and lead the rest.
The team itself, would ideally be formed based on experience and deep understanding of the subject matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great open source projects exist and survive, thanks to how well coordinated and organized they are.
There is always something to be done by someone at multiple levels, layers or fields,
Such projects would not survive if every contributor decides he’d only contribute code patches, or if technical decisions are made based on assumptions such as “we will choose x technology because its easy and we want more people to contribute code”.
Fennecs suffered from the latter, and is dying slowly and painfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="better-ideas"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Better ideas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As i said earlier, I felt that this whole webOS thing was a bad idea, it certainly wouldn’t improve the daily lives of algerians, not to mention that it’s not meant to be used by regular &lt;em&gt;non tech wizards&lt;/em&gt; people who barely know what a web browser is. and thus it wouldn&amp;amp;rsquo;t have made a big impact as some thought it would.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given how weak, empty, and broken our web is and how much we would love that to change;
A better idea would be to build something that benefits from crowdsourcing capabilities of the web, organize information contributed by users and present it in interesting ways
following models and approaches such as &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/"&gt;Openstreetmap&lt;/a&gt;. 's to cartography, i&amp;amp;rsquo;m sure it can be applied to many other fields, and certain that it would benefit more than a bunch of algerian techies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="operating systems"></category><category term="bad ideas"></category><category term="open source"></category><category term="algeria"></category></entry><entry><title>Envoyés Spéciaux Algeriens - Yet another blown chance</title><link href="http://redouanezait.com/esa-yet-another-blown-chance.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-02-10T21:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Redouane Zait</name></author><id>tag:redouanezait.com,2012-02-10:esa-yet-another-blown-chance.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PS : ESA stands for Envoyées spéciaux Algeriens.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classic media is run and controlled by entities which among other things, censor content based on their own interest and do not report everything,
most of these medias follow the &amp;quot;update our news website once a day&amp;quot; model, which is outdated and is put to shame by the speed at which news and word flows in social media sites like twitter and facebook
basicly, these guys just dont get it and probably won't until its too late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.facebook.com/e.s.algeriens"&gt;ESA&lt;/a&gt;. is a facebook page run by a couple of regular guys, trying to fulfill the &lt;em&gt;urgent&lt;/em&gt; need for a decentralised news source in algeria, they currently have nearly 100k likes, which is &lt;em&gt;quite alot&lt;/em&gt; for an algerian page, and you'll want to turn those numbers into something that makes more sense than a facebook page, which brings us to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="make-something-people-want"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Make something people want&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ycombinator.com"&gt;YCombinator&lt;/a&gt; 's motto, basicly if you wanna succeed, you'll have to make something that will affect the daily lives of algerians, and there arent that many things to chose from, heck, such a list does not even exist given how young and hard-to-understand the algerian web market is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-esa-case"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The ESA case&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the idea is simple yet so powerful, the need is there, and so are the users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, ESA launched their very much hyped &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://nessnews.com"&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt;. , it's ugly, feels old already, no innovation whatsoever, it looks like a regular, classic media website.
it turns out ESA also don't get it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;now, making a realtime user based news and events site is neither a trivial task nor a hard one
but spending months tweaking a joomla site using a wysiwyg app or something like that, to launch a possibly 100k+ users website is just hilarious and laughable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i herby officially add ESA to my joomla &lt;em&gt;( or any CMS for that matter )&lt;/em&gt; victim list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="media"></category><category term="news"></category><category term="algeria"></category><category term="facebook"></category><category term="CMS"></category></entry><entry><title>Réussir sur la toile Algérienne</title><link href="http://redouanezait.com/reussir-sur-toile-algerienne.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-06-10T21:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Redouane Zait</name></author><id>tag:redouanezait.com,2011-06-10:reussir-sur-toile-algerienne.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sur la toile algérienne, il Manque tout, sauf les sites d'annonces, chaque 'dlala&amp;quot; de quartier à son propre site d'annonce,
ouedkniss, la3kiba, ou meme un certain &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://i.imgur.com/Zdb0Y.jpg"&gt;bachdjarrah&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;désormais, tout le monde à son propre site d'annonces, mais pourquoi donc ? Cherchent ils tous le success de oudkniss ? .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Retour en 2006, Oued kniss le vrai, est menacé de fermeture, ils sautent sur l'ocasion et enregistrent le domaine, leur raison d'etre est de réouvrir le marché, cette fois en ligne, Puis un article à la techcrunch du quotidien El Watan, du bouche à l'oreil. bref, Bon endroit, Bon moment, et surtout bonne execution, ouedkniss est désormais la premiere déstination pour publier ses annonces en algérie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pour battre le &amp;quot;King&amp;quot;, faut apporter quelque chose de nouveau à la table, mais pourquoi chercher à battre ouedkniss ? pourquoi ne pas tenter quelque chose d'autre de nouveau
ce déséquilibre de services web, est il du au manque d'idées ou de compétences techniques ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="une-idee-sans-implementation-ne-vaut-rien"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Une idée sans implémentation ne vaut rien&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
si vous etes pas dévelopeur et que vous n'arrivez pas à former une bonne équipe, d'amis proches de préference, oubliez.
si vous etes égoiste et que vous cherchez à tout faire en solo, oubliez.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="une-implementation-d-une-idee-pourrie-ne-vaut-rien-non-plus"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Une implémentation d'une idée pourrie ne vaut rien non plus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
c'est simple, si votre idée n'améliore pas le quotidient des algériens, ces derniers ne vont pas chercher à utiliser votre service
vous allez souffrir d'une mort rapide, ainsi qu'une perte de confidence.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="une-implementation-pourrie-d-une-bonne-idee-est-dangereux"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Une implémentation pourrie d'une bonne idée est dangereux&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
il est clair que pour réussir faut avoir ou connaitre des gens qui ont de bonnes compétences techniques dans les domaines relatives à votre idée
les sites vite fait avec des CMS ne servent à rien, à part prouver l'incompétence et l'impatience de leur propriétaires, sans parler du risque de voir son reve s'envoler si quelquen d'autre décide de reprendre et implémenter votre idée, je sais pas comment les brevets d'invetions marchent en algérie, mais ca risque d'etre chaud.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;L'idéal serait de penser à quelque chose,former une equipe, tenter le coup en créant un prototype, voir les réactions, puis itérer et lancer le service au bon moment. si ca marche pas c'est pas grave, &amp;quot;experience is what you get when you dont get what you want&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;le web algérien est encore jeune, et c'est pas les idées qui manquent, ya beaucoup de problèmes intéressants à tacler, alors à vos stylos! .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="algeria"></category><category term="startups"></category><category term="ideas"></category></entry></feed>